Guide to the William Hicks and Marjorie Alma Tice McIver Papers, 1882-1974 RL.11888
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
William Hicks and Marjorie Alma Tice McIver Papers
1882-1974
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
McIver, William Hicks, 1898-1979
Hicks, Marjorie Alma (Tice), 1898-1982
RL.11888
1.5 Linear Feet 2 document boxes
The McIvers lived in Winston-Salem, North Carolina, in the early and mid-20th century. This collection contains postcard albums with examples of tourism postcards and seasonal or holiday cards collected by William McIver's family in the 1910s-1920s, as well as letters sent to Marjorie McIver from elected officials responding to her opinions on pending legislation, like the Bardon Education Bill. The collection contains examples of anti-Communist and anti-Catholic pamphlets and printed materials from the 1950s and 1960s, as well as a Pickrick Drumstick autographed by Lester Maddox. These drumsticks were wooden pick ax handles were used to threaten Black Georgia Tech students seeking to integrate the Pickrick Cafeteria restaurant in Atlanta in 1964, and later used as segregationist symbols sold as souvenirs during Maddox's 1966 gubanatorial campaign.
Biographical / Historical
According to U.S. Census and Virginia marriage records, William Hicks McIver was a white man born August 13, 1898 in Sanford, North Carolina, to Abigail Chaffin and John Henry McIver. He worked as a tobacco foreman in the 1930s and married Marjorie Tice Marshall, then a widow, on March 28, 1932. Marjorie was a white woman born July 4, 1898, in Columbus, Indiana.
William served in World War II, but we are not sure in what capacity. The couple lived in Winston-Salem, North Carolina, and had no children. William McIver died on January 8, 1979. Marjorie died on October 8, 1982, in Durham, North Carolina.
It has been challenging to learn more about the history of this family. Census research confirmed that Mattie McIver, the recipient of many of the postcards held in the collection, was William's older sister, who was born in approximately 1893 in Germanton, N.C.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The William Hicks and Marjorie Alma Tice McIver Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift from Roger L. Marshall in 1981.
The original accession included unmounted and loose postcards, which were filed in the Postcard Collection at the point of acquisition, in 1981.
Collection Overview
This collection contains 3 postcard albums with examples of tourism postcards and seasonal or holiday cards collected by William McIver's family, largely his sister, Mattie McIver, during the 1910s. There is a folder of letters sent to Marjorie McIver from elected officials responding to her opinions on pending legislation. Topics include Congressman Graham A. Barden's Federal Aid to Education Bill, prayer in public schools, President Kennedy's tax proposal, and the Vietnam War. The collection contains examples of anti-Communist and anti-Catholic pamphlets and printed materials from the 1950s and 1960s, as well as a Pickrick Drumstick autographed by Lester Maddox. These drumsticks were wooden pick ax handles were used to threaten Black Georgia Tech students seeking to integrate the Pickrick Cafeteria restaurant in Atlanta in 1964, and later used as segregationist symbols sold as souvenirs during Maddox's 1966 Georgia gubanatorial campaign.
Propaganda, Anti-communist; Nativism; Racism -- United States -- History; Postcards -- Collectors and collecting; Postcards -- United States; Race discrimination; Anti-Catholicism; Civil rights -- Georgia -- History -- 20th century; Winston-Salem (N.C.); Maddox, Lester, 1915-2003; McIver, Mattie F, 1893-
- Postcard album: blue spiral. Addressed to Mattie McIver, 1910s (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Postcards featuring Winston-Salem, Florida, holiday greetings (Easter, Christmas), and Independence Park (Philadelphia) portraits of founding fathers.
- Postcard album: red spiral Photo Album. Addressed to variety of people, including Mattie McIver, 1910s (Box 1)
  Album with examples of postcards with holiday greetings, as well as some Florida and NC postcards. Some World War I photo postcards, including an image of a group hanging in Dalmatia, captioned "people hung by Germans for treason, Spalato, Dalmatia, 1919".
- Postcard album: green 3-ring binding., 1910s-1950s (Box 1)
  Tourist postcards, including some N.C., S.C., Tennessee, Wisconsin, Colorado, Yosemite, Washington D.C., as well as seasonal greetings.
- Correspondence to Marjorie McIver from various elected officials, 1946-1974 (Box 2)
  Includes congressmen, senators, and governors responding to her letters. She appears to have supported Federal Aid to Education Bill (1949); opposed the war in Vietnam; opposed federal overspending; supported a constitutional amendment regarding prayer in public school (1974). Letters are from Sam Ervin, Ronald Reagan, and William Umstead, among others.
- Niagara Falls tourism snapshots, 1940s (Box 2)
- Vaccination certificate (variola) for Louis Barett, 1882 (Box 2)
- Ration books for the McIvers, William McIver draft cards, and red tokens from World War II, 1940s (Box 2)
- Winston-Salem local history ephemera, including church directories, programs, 1956-1960s (Box 2)
- Circulars from the National Defense Committee, National Society for the Daughters of the American Revolution, 1959 (Box 2)
  Expressing anti-Communist views.
- Anti-Communist and Anti-Catholic printed materials, 1930s-1960s (Box 2)
- Lester Maddox's Pickrick Drumstick, autographed by Maddox, 1966 (Box 2)
  This item is an example of a Pickrick Drumstick, which were wooden pick ax handles used to threaten Black Georgia Tech students and protestors seeking to integrate the Pickrick Cafeteria restaurant in Atlanta in 1964, and later adopted by Maddox as a segregationist symbol. Maddox sold these drumsticks as souvenirs after closing his restaurant rather than agree to integration. This item appears to date from Maddox's gubanatorial campaign in 1966. Unknown how the McIvers acquired this item, or when.